Guide to the John George Herriot Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John George Herriot papers
1937-1992
SC0745
Herriot, John George, 1916-
8 Linear feet
These papers document his career as a mathematician and include his notes taken while a student at Brown University, 1937-41, and his master's and doctoral theses, 1940-41; research files (notes, computations, articles, computer printouts, some correspondence, and other materials) on Fourier series, Schlicht functions, spline theory, and other topics, 1940-83; memos, minutes, correspondence, and other records pertaining to Stanford's Dept. of Computer Sciences and the Stanford Computation Center, 1946-92; correspondence, notes, and reports pertaining to his Fulbright year, 1962-63; and bibliographic and biographical materials. Other persons represented in the papers include Carl De Boor, C. H. Reinsch, and Larry L. Schumaker.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
John G. Herriot earned his B.S. in mathematics and physics at the University of Manitoba in 1937 and his Ph.D. in mathematics at Brown University in 1941. He first taught at Stanford from 1942-1944, leaving to do research in the Ames Aeronautical Laboratory at Moffett Field. He returned to Stanford in 1946 as assistant professor of mathematics, becoming full professor in 1956; he retired from teaching in 1982. He served as the first directory of the Stanford Computation Center, 1953-61, taught the first programming course at Stanford in 1955, and helped found the computer science department at Stanford in 1965. He died in 2003.
Description of the Collection
These papers document his career as a mathematician and include his notes taken while a student at Brown University, 1937-41, and his master's and doctoral theses, 1940-41; research files (notes, computations, articles, computer printouts, some correspondence, and other materials) on Fourier series, Schlicht functions, spline theory, and other topics, 1940-83; memos, minutes, correspondence, and other records pertaining to Stanford's Dept. of Computer Sciences and the Stanford Computation Center, 1946-92; correspondence, notes, and reports pertaining to his Fulbright year, 1962-63; and bibliographic and biographical materials. Other persons represented in the papers include Carl De Boor, C. H. Reinsch, and Larry L. Schumaker.
Access Terms
De Boor, Carl.; Herriot, John George, 1916-; Reinsch, C. H.; Schumaker, Larry L., 1939-; Stanford University. Computer Science Department.; Stanford University. Department of Mathematics.; Fourier integral operators.; Mathematical analysis.; Mathematics --Study and teaching (Higher).; Numerical analysis.; Spline theory.; Univalent functions.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2005-069
  - Research files
    - Capacity – check of Aissen, Haegi, Ullman (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Capacity – Polya 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Capacity 1948 (1) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Capacity 1948 (2) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Capacity 1948 (3) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ames 755 (Laitone – subsonic flow) 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ames 4412 (shock waves) 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cauchy's problem 3rd order (1) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cauchy's problem 3rd order (2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cauchy's problem 3rd order (3) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Matrix D.E. – adjoint (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Lens (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lens (2) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lens polarization (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 0
    - Lens 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Fov. Series proposed work (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Analytic function with a singular line (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Free boundary flows (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mapping – lecture notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Fou. Series – thesis (1 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Fou. Series – thesis (2 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Fou. Series – thesis (3 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Restricted Reist summability (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Fou. Series. Preliminary calculations. Doc. thesis (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Fou. Series (Orders of Infinity) – thesis (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fou. Series and other topics – papers presented 1940-50 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Cesano summability (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - D. D. S. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Th'M Proofs (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Flow – Polya notes, 1940- (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Fou. Series 1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Tunnel blockage corrections, JO 837 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Tunnel blockage corrections, JO 837 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - [History notes re mathematics] (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Restricted Reist summability (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Brown U. math Ph.D.s 1946 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Historical material 1946-66 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Schlicht fcns [functions] (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Schlicht functions (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Schlicht fcns (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Schlicht fcns (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Schlicht fcns (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Schlicht fcns (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Schlicht fcns (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Schlicht functions (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Schlicht fcns (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Odd Schlicht functions – UN-23 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - UN-23 (1, 2, 3, 4) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - UN-23 (5-12) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - UN-23 (13-16) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - [Odd Schlicht functions – UN-23] (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Odd Schlicht functions (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Odd Schlicht functions – program (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Odd Schlicht functions (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Odd Schlicht functions (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Odd Schlicht functions by = 1.01 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Garrett Birkhoff, correspondence May 1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Forsythe ONR contract 1958-69 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Bierberbach-De Branges (paper by Walter Gautschi) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - UN-23 by=1.0064635 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Henrici NA symposium, Zurich 1983, paper [by Herriot] (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Boundary values symposium, U. of Wisconsin, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Notes from AMS meeting, Seattle, Aug. 1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - AFCALTI, Toulouse 1963 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - ICM Warsaw 1982-83 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Algol to CACM Sept. 1960 [corrections to algorithm 15] (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Bergman-Herriot [drafts, notes, computations for paper], 1965 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Copies of paper submitted to IFIP 68, November 1967 [On the Numerical Calculation of Transonic Flow Patterns by Bergman's Integral Operator] (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Bergman - problems (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Bergman-Herriot, notes and computations (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Bergman – Herriot (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Bergman-Herriot-Richman, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Bergman-Herriot, early calculations (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Herriot-Bergman paper [Computation of a Class of Subsonic Flow Patterns], Numerische Mathematik, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Bergman-Herriot results 1960-61 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - IBM meeting photo, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Annals of the History of Computing, IBM 650, May 1984 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Computer Center Division meeting 1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Complete Spline 1980-81, MDRBLD development - 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Complete Spline 1980-81, MDRBLD development - 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Complete Splines 1980-81 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Spline function NATSPLINE Development (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Spline functions seminar, Tech. Huch. Munchen, W.S. 1969/70 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Complete Spline 4-80 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Reinsch notes – Spline stuff, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Complete Spline Spring 1983 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Com Spline Fall 1982 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Complete Spine: letters to Coughran and changes 1980-81 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Spline files at SCIP and run of pubtests, 1975/76 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - NATSPINE 1976-77 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - de Boor – Perfect Splines 1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Complete Spline: M=1 case 9-80 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Complete Spline: Cochran tests 1981 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Quintic Spline – Reinsch CS 402 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Herriot – original of submission to Alg Dept 6-17-74 ("Procedures for Quintic Natural Spline Interpolation [E1]") (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Alg 472 changes (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Splines – smoothing – Reinsch / Forsythe correspondence (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Splines – Herriot reprints (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Complete splines scaling attempts 1982 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Complete splines decay tests 1981 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - NSF – statements (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Mathematical and Computational Science, S.U. undergraduate booklets, 1989-92 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - History of Scientific and Numeric Computation [conference], 1987 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Splines – comments on paper of John R. Rice, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Spline functions seminar, Madison, May 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Spline functions seminar SU, Summer 1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Alg 472, inquiry from Emily C. M. Funk, 1974 [includes photos of graphs] (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Spline functions literature (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Splines – Reinsch algs listings 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Alg 507/600 translation (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Submitted to Algorithms (Alg 507), 1974 [mostly correspondence] (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Spline – Quintic – Morgana (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Reinsch (Christian) correspondence (Splines) 1973-76 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - References of interest Splines and others (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - CUB NATSPINE / NATSPINE using de Boor 1976 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Splines CS-71-200 – changes and additional errata (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Splines Schumaker 6-76 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Schumaker (Larry) correspondence, Splines, 1975-77 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - de Boor example, no response, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - B-Splines - de Boor 1976 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Complete Spline 1976-77 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Spline tests – Natspline and DEBNAT 1976 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Splines – B-Splines – de Boor, 1975-77 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Splines – NATSPLINE – Lewis (John) mod, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Spline talks, Australia and Zurich, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Spline talks, Australia and Zurich - overhead slides, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Int. Conference of Mathematicians, Quintic Natural Splines, Aug. 1974 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - NUM ANAL – Spline functions – SU, April 18, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Coughran, Herriot – refereeing 1983 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Coughran complete splines 1976-77 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Splines – Alg 472-CACM Dec. 1973 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Splines – Alg 472-CACM 1973 Reprints (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Spline notes 1969-71 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Unlabelled materials [correspondence and notes re NATSPLINE?] (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Unlabelled materials [notes re compressible fluids?] (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Reprint of H. Spath with correspondence, 1970, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Reprint of C. S. Duris with correspondence 1975 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Engineering rules (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Stanford University files
    - Computer Science Dept., Advisory Committee, photo, Oct. 1967 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Computer Science Dept., early theses, 1960-70 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Computer Science Dept., memos, minutes, etc., 1971-74 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Computer Science Dept., memos, minutes, etc., 1989-90 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Computer Science Dept., memos, minutes, etc., 1991-92 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Forsythe (George) memorials (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Mandatory retirement discussion, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Math Dept., search committee, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Mu Alpha Theta, Stanford meeting, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Obituaries – Polya and Szego (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Patent agreement: SU – JGH (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Polya (George) memorial resolutions (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Ratings of Computer Science Department (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Retirement, 1981-83 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Sabbatical rules and applications, 1969-79 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Stanford Computation Center – early history, 1953-61 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Stanford Computation Center Research reports catalogue 1964 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Stanford Computation Center status, NSF letters 1954-56 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Stanford – High School math exams 1946-55 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Fulbright, Sabbatical, and Other Travel Files
    - Fullbright application – notes, correspondence 1961 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Fullbright – correspondence and reports, 1962-63 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Fullbright 1962-63 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Fullbright and other trips, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - General information – European travels, 1962-63 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Groupe de Travail d'Analyse Numerique – Grenoble 1962-63 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Fulbright materials (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - IFIP travel, IFIP Congress 1968 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Sabbatical 1980, Munich, correspondence including ETH (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Travel records 1978-83 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Biographical, bibliographic, and personal files
    - Biography, bibliography [Herriot] (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Interview with John Herriot conducted by Pamela McCorduck, Charles Babbage Institute, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Reprints sent (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Inventory [mathematical journals dispersed to libraries] (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Student Notebooks
    - Notebook: Proj. Geom. Probs. Book I, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Notebook: Proj. Geom. Probs. Book II, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Notebook: Algebra (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Notebook: Algebra Book II (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Notebook: Analysis 1 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Notebook: Analysis 2 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Notebook: Analysis 3 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Notebook: Analysis – abstract spaces (Differential Geometry) 1938-39 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Notebook: Maths. V Probs. (Differential equations) 1937 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Notebook: Maths. V Mechanics, Complex Variables (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Notebook: Mechanics [and possibly other topics] (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Notebook: untitled, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Notebook: Herriot, "Cesaro Summability of Ordinary Double Dirichlet Series" (Brown University master's thesis 1938); Herriot, "Tides and Tide Prediction" Brown University 1940 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Notebook: Herriot, "Norlund Summability of Double Fourier Series" (Brown University Ph.D. thesis 1941) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Class notes by Herriot, Brown University: Theory of Functions of One Real Variable (Prof. C. R. Adams) 1937-38 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Class notes by Herriot, Brown University: Theory of Probabilities (Prof. J. D. Tamarkin) 1938-39 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Class notes by Herriot, Brown University: Theory of Integration Linear Functionals etc. (Prof. J. D. Tamarkin) 1940-41 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - [Class notes by Herriot, Brown University]: on introductory theorems, computation of Fourier series, convergence of Fourier series, summability of Fourier series, complex methods in Fourier series, and absolute convergence of Fourier series, n.d. [no title page but same binding as previous Brown University notebooks] (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Writings and reprints
    - Herriot, "Calculation of particular solutions of linear partial differential equations by the method of integral operators," n.d. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Herriot et. al., "Bell Floating-Decimal interpretive system for the Burroughs 220," Stanford University Computation Center, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Reprints of Herriot's articles 1940s (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Reprints of Herriot's articles 1950s (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Reprints of Herriot's articles 1960s-80s (Box 17)